The setup here starts with a cylinder full of sugar water basically
这个装置基本上先是一个装满糖水的圆柱
糖水
(0.75g 蔗糖/mL 水）
and we're about to shine some white light into it.
我们准备拿白光来照它
白光
（无偏振）
But before it gets there, it passes through a linearly polarizing filter.
但光线到达圆柱之前  要先通过一个线偏振片
线偏振片
（可变角度）
And what that means basically
简单来说就是
线偏振片
is that if you look at all of the light waves beyond the point of that filter
若观测通过偏振片后的所有光波
those waves are only going to be wiggling in one direction, say up and down.
会发现那些波都只沿一个方向振荡  比如上下振荡
And don't worry, in a few minutes we're going to go into much more detail about
别着急  我们很快将会更仔细地探讨
what specifically is wiggling
具体是什么在振荡
and what the significance of that wiggling direction is
以及振荡方向为何重要
but skipping to the punch line first
但我们先跳到重点
线偏振片
（可变角度）
the demo also includes a second linearly polarizing filter coming out the other end
这个装置的另一端还有第二个线偏振片
and I want you to predict what we're going to see once we turn the light on.
我想请你预测一下  开灯后我们会看到什么
Steve Mould不是讲过了吗？
Now I suspect some viewers might already have a little bit of a sense for what's going on
我猜一些观众也许已经有点头绪了
because a few years ago Steve Mould made a really excellent video
因为几年前  Steve Mould 做了一期非常棒的视频
about this phenomenon of shining polarized light through sugar water.
讲的就是偏振光经过糖水的这个现象
It was really well done, which is no surprise because everything Steve makes is.
视频非常好  毕竟 Steve 出品必属精品
But even if you watched that, this is a rich enough phenomenon that there's still more to be explained.
但就算你看过那个视频  这个丰富的现象仍有需要解释的地方
接下来···
In fact even if you you made that video
甚至就算你本人做了那期视频
this is a rich enough phenomenon that there's more to be explained.
这个丰富的现象依然有需要解释的地方
I'm curious Steve, when you made that video
Steve 我很好奇  当你做视频的时候
did you happen to get a good view of the side of the glass
有没有好好地看圆柱的侧面呢
probably when the rest of the lights in the room were off or something like that?
例如  关掉房间里其他灯再看  什么的
No, no, I didn't think about the side view.
没有  没有  我没想过要看侧边
Great, so given the setup that we're looking at now
好嘞  那么你看看这一套装置
once we turn off the room lights and turn on the lamp
等下我们关掉房间灯  打开白灯后
I'm curious if you have a prediction for what you might see.
我很好奇你能不能预测出看到的情形呢
Well, there will be some scattering I suppose
嗯  我猜会有一些散射
but then if we're just looking at the tube
但如果只是盯着圆管来看
we're not applying any kind of filter to just look into it to the tube.
也不加什么滤光片  直接看圆管的话
So I mean my instinct is nothing
我的直觉是  无事发生
you know, nothing will happen.
就啥也不会发生
That would have been my guess too
我当时也是这样猜的
but let me just show you what it looks like when we turn off the room lights and we turn on the lamp.
不过我直接演示吧  关掉房间灯打开白灯后会如何
And then if you turn the initial polarizer you can kind of see those stripes
此时转动第一个偏振片  就会看到这些色带
those diagonal Stripes seem to walk up the tube.
斜向色带似乎会沿着圆管走
Oh, wow.
哇
But why diagonal?
但为什么是斜的呢
Exactly, why diagonal?
问得好  为什么会斜呢
But why anything
但为什么啊
I mean why anything?
为什么会有这一切啊
Something about the interaction with sugar water
跟糖水发生某种互动后
separates the light out into these different bands of color.
光被分成了不同的色带
but it does so in this really intriguing way
而且  规律非常耐人寻味
with the colors appear to form these spiral helixes down the tube.
颜色沿着圆管  形成了螺旋的形状
and the other thing I want to draw your attention to
另一个请注意看的点是
is the color that's coming out of the tube after it passes through that second filter.
通过第二个偏振片后  从圆管出来的色彩
注意看照出来的颜色
As we rotate the first filter, you rotate through a family of distinct hues.
不断转动第一个偏振片  就会看到一系列不同的色调
And it doesn't have to be the first filter
而且不只是第一偏振片
if you rotate that second filter you also rotate through these various different colors.
当你转动第二偏振片时  也会看到各种颜色
That's Quinn by the way, who kindly set up this whole demo
另外这是 Quinn  感谢她摆放了这套装置
and what I love about this setup is that if you want to really understand what you're looking at
我很喜欢这套装置的一点是  要想真正理解眼前所见
with that deep to your bones satisfying sense of what's going on
要想刻骨铭心地理解这些原理
it requires having very solid intuitions for a number of different fundamental concepts about light
那你就得对光的许多基本概念  有很扎实的直觉
like polarization, how scattering works, and how an index of refraction works.
例如  偏振  散射原理  以及折射率原理
To kick things off, let me show you the overall structure for the explanation of what's going on here
首先  让我展示解释该现象的整体框架
偏振
散射
折射率
首先：大纲
and along the way record various questions that we still need to answer.
并且一路记下我们仍需回答的各个问题
A basic premise to the whole thing is to think about polarized light
这一切的基本前提是  将偏振光视为
as a propagating wave which is wiggling in just one direction.
只沿一个方向振荡的传播波
问题 0：到底是什么在振荡？
And I suppose question number zero is for us to be clear about what exactly is wiggling.
也许第零个问题是  先搞清楚究竟是什么在振荡
Postponing that for the moment
暂且按下不表
we will just say if we think about it as propagating in one direction, say along an x-axis
先假设这个波沿着一个方向传播  如 x 轴
the wiggling happens perpendicular to that, say in the z-direction.
振荡方向与其垂直  假设沿着 z 轴
What's going on when it passes through this tube of sugar water
偏振光通过这个糖水管后的情况是
is that that wiggling direction gets twisted.
振荡方向会发生旋转
问题 1：为什么糖旋转了方向？
And so the first key question is why?
于是第一个关键问题:  这是为什么呢
What is it about interaction with sugar that causes this twist?
光与糖的相互作用  为何会导致其旋转呢
And just so that it's crystal clear what I mean by twisting
我解释一下这里的旋转是什么意思
if you focus your attention on a single slice perpendicular to the axis of the cylinder
注意看垂直于圆柱中心轴的截面
and draw a line indicating how the light is wiggling on that slice
然后画一条线  表示光在截面上的振荡方向
then if you were to move that slice down the cylinder
那么随着截面沿圆柱移动
the relevant wiggling direction slowly turns about the axis of the cylinder.
相应的振荡方向  也会沿着圆柱中心轴缓慢转动
Critically, the rate at which it's getting twisted depends on the frequency of the light.
关键在于  旋转速率取决于光的频率
Higher frequency light, say violet,
高频的光  例如紫色光
actually gets twisted more quickly than low frequency light like red.
比低频的光  例如红色光  要旋转得更快
问题 2：为什么旋转速率取决于频率？
So the second key question we need to answer is:
那么要回答的第二个关键问题就是
why would that twisting rate depend on the frequency?
为什么旋转速率取决于频率呢
Whatever explanation we come to for why the twisting happens in the first place
我们在第一问中  关于光为什么会旋转的解释
it should offer some intuition for where the dependence on frequency would come from.
理应能提供一些直觉  说明其跟频率的关系从何而来
Let's take a moment to think about what it means
仔细时间想想这是什么意思
that different colors of light are getting twisted at different rates.
不同颜色的光  旋转速率不同
In the demo we're shining in white light
在演示中我们照射的是白光
and white light is not a clean pure sine wave, it's something more complicated
而白光不是纯净的正弦波  其要更为复杂
and you typically think about it as a combination of many different pure sine waves
通常可以将其视为  多个不同正弦波的组合
each one corresponding to one of the colors in the rainbow.
每一个正弦波  对应彩虹中的一个颜色
For this animation I will schematically represent the wiggling direction for each pure frequency
在动画中  我把每个单独频率的振荡方向
just with a line.
抽象地表示为一条线
so the key idea is that as all of those different waves propagate down the tube
关键思想就是  随着这些不同的波  沿着管子传播
with different pure frequencies twisting at different rates
不同的纯频率  旋转速率不同
purple light twisting the fastest and red light twisting the slowest
紫光转得最快  红光转得最慢
then the polarization directions for each one of those pure colors gets separated out.
那么各个纯色的偏振方向  就会互相区分开来
for example by the time you reach the end of the tube
例如  到达管子的末端时
they all have their own distinct wiggling directions.
不同的颜色各有不同的振荡方向
But one thing that's important to understand is that this is still white light.
但有一点必须明白  这仍然是白光
这仍是白光
If you were to put your eye at the end of the tube and look towards the lamp
如果从管子末端  向着灯光望去
it wouldn't look colored in any way
看起来不会有任何颜色
这仍是白光
because even if the wiggling directions are all different
因为即使振荡方向各不相同
they're still the same amount of each color as there was at the start.
每种颜色的光量  仍与开始时一样
in order to see any evidence of the separation
要看到颜色分离的迹象
one thing you could do is pass it all through a second linear polarizing filter,
可以做的是  将其通过第二个线偏振片
say in the vertical direction.
比如放在垂直方向
The effect that has is that the amount of light of a given frequency passing through
其效果是  特定频率光的通过量
is equal to the component of its polarization direction that lines up with the filter.
等于其偏振方向  在滤光片方向上的分量
So colors which happen to align very closely with that filter pass through almost completely
因此  恰好旋转到很接近滤光片方向的光  几乎完全通过
whereas colors which end up more perpendicular to the filter pass through only very weakly.
而旋转到与滤光片方向近乎垂直的光  几乎不通过
So the light coming out the other end of this filter
因此  从滤光片另一端射出的光
is some imbalanced combination of all of the pure frequencies
是所有纯频率光的某种不均匀组合
which is why what we see coming out the other end is no longer white but some other color.
这就是为什么  另一端射出的光不再是白色  而是其他颜色
注意看照出来的颜色
And notice if we rotate the whole setup, say by twisting the initial polarizing filter
注意  如果我们旋转整个装置  比如旋转初始偏振片
then that changes the components of each pure frequency that happen to be vertical
那这就会改变  每个纯频率光  与滤光片方向垂直的分量
resulting in a different balance of all those colors
从而导致不同的颜色混合比例
which is why rotating the initial filter changes the color you see coming out the other end.
这就是为什么  旋转初始偏振片  会改变另一端出射光的颜色
And this is something you can do at home by the way, you don't need a very fancy setup.
你在家其实就能做这个实验  并不需要多么豪华的配置
Start by creating a pretty dense mixture of sugar water
首先制备浓稠的糖水
and then you'll need to get your hands on some polarizing filters
然后准备一些偏振片
so that you can pass light first through one of those filters
这样就能让光先穿过其中一个偏振片
then through the sugar water, and then through a second filter
然后穿过糖水  再穿过第二个偏振片
and if you look at this whole setup from the top as you rotate one of those filters,
从顶部观察整个装置  当你旋转其中一个偏振片时
you'll see different colors.
就能看到不同的颜色
But even if you understand this
但即使你明白这一点
the thing that really had me scratching my head when Quinn showed me this demo
当 Quinn 向我演示时  真正让我摸不着头脑的是
问题 3：
为什么会看到斜向色带？
was why you would see diagonal stripes when you view the cylinder from the side?
为什么从侧面看圆柱  会看到斜向色带
I mean, take a moment to think about this.
花点时间想想这个问题
At any point down the tube, even though all the colors have been rotated differently
在管子的任一点  即使所有的颜色都旋转了不同角度
again the light at that point is still white, it's still an equal balance of all the different colors.
该点处的光仍然是白色的  仍然是所有不同颜色的等量组合
这仍是白光
If you were to stick your eye inside the tube and look towards the lamp
如果你将眼睛伸进管子内  并朝灯光望去
这仍是白光
you would see white,
你会看到白色
so why would viewing it from the side change what you see?
那为什么从侧面看就会有不同呢
The way I've made this animation I've just left a faint shadow
我做动画时留下了一个隐约的影像
representing the wiggling direction for each color along the way down the tube
来表示每种颜色在管内的振荡方向
but that's just a cartoon - it's a schematic representation.
但这只是个动画  只是个示意图
这里没有偏振片！
Why is it that the actual way that light interacts with the molecules within the tube
实际情况下  为什么光与管内分子的相互作用
would discriminate between the colors in any way?
会以任何方式分离颜色呢
问题 3：
为什么会看到斜向色带？
and why would the stripes be diagonal?
而且为什么色带是斜向的呢
Wouldn't you think the setup should be completely symmetric from top to bottom?
这个装置难道不是完全上下对称的吗
So these are the main questions we need to answer.
这就是我们要回答的几个主要问题
余留的问题
问题 1：为什么糖旋转了光？
Why would sugar cause the light to twist?
为什么糖会旋转光
Why would the rate at which it twists depend on the frequency of the light?
为什么旋转速率取决于光的频率
问题 2：为什么旋转速率取决于频率？
And why, even if you understand both those facts
以及为什么  即使你知道这两个的答案
问题 3：为什么会看到斜向色带？
would you be seeing different colors appear in these diagonal stripes?
为什么会看到不同的颜色  呈现出斜向色带
You can answer these questions if you have a handful of key intuitions about optics.
如果你对光学有一些关键直觉  就能回答这些问题
The first question requires understanding circularly polarized light
问题一  要求理解圆偏振光
since the key is that sucrose is a chiral molecule
因为关键是  蔗糖是一种手性分子
which is to say there's a handedness to it, it's different from its mirror image
手性的意思是  镜像与自身不同
and the slightly different effects that it has
以及其对右旋、左旋圆偏振光  略微不同的影响
on right-handed versus left-handed circularly polarized light
ends up explaining the twist.
最终解释了这种旋转
The second question requires understanding
问题二  要求理解的是
why light appears to slow down when it passes through a material.
为什么光在穿过物质时  会减速
A sufficiently mathematical understanding for where that slowdown comes from
先从数学角度充分地理解了光速变慢的原因
ultimately explains the color separation here.
就能最终解释色彩为何会分离
And the third question comes down to the fact that when light scatters off of a material
而问题三涉及到这样一个事实  当光从某种物质上散射时
it's not like some projectile bouncing in any old direction -
它并不像弹丸那样往任意方向上反弹
the direction of scattering depends on the direction of polarization,
散射方向取决于偏振方向
and there's a very good reason for it.
这是有充分理由的
权威解答
My aim is for all of these answers to feel less like facts that I'm handing down from on high
我的目标是  让所有这些答案不像是从天而降的事实
and more like inevitable discoveries emerging from a fundamental understanding for what light actually is.
而更像是  从对光的基本理解中  领悟得出的必然发现
基本理解
For that, we will begin by returning to that question number zero:
为此  我们得回到问题零
What exactly is wiggling?
到底是什么在振荡
Which is to say, what is light?
也就是在问  光是什么
If you're curious about how the full explanation unfolds, come join me in the next video.
如果你想层层揭开问题的谜团  请随我一同观看下一条视频
It's really surprising, I'm really surprised.
真的很令人惊讶  我被惊讶到了
You notice it in person as well presumably,
想必用肉眼也能看到吧
it's not just something that appears in the camera.
应该不是只能用相机拍的东西
It's actually more striking in person I think,
其实用肉眼看更显著
just because of like how the color of the camera works
我想这是因为相机处理色彩的方式
it's more intense in person.
肉眼看更鲜艳
I mean it's for the same reason you can't take a good picture of a rainbow
我想这就和无法拍好彩虹照片的原因是一样的
as if our brains do something to make rainbows more vibrant than they really are.
就像我们的大脑做了一些事情  来让彩虹看起来比实际更鲜艳一样